<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://lab.depositar.io/feed/news.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://lab.depositar.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><updated>2025-02-20T14:14:31+08:00</updated><id>https://lab.depositar.io/feed/news.xml</id><title type="html">depositar lab | News</title><subtitle>The website of the depositar lab. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Research Data Management and Sharing – a short talk by the depositar team at the Institute of Earth Sciences, Academia Sinica</title><link href="https://lab.depositar.io/news/250220/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Research Data Management and Sharing – a short talk by the depositar team at the Institute of Earth Sciences, Academia Sinica"/><published>2025-02-20T10:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2025-02-20T10:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://lab.depositar.io/news/250220</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lab.depositar.io/news/250220/"><![CDATA[<p>On February 13, 2025, the depositar team was invited by the Institute of Earth Sciences at the Academia Sinica to share experience about research data management during their weekly Geotalk event.</p> <p>In the short talk, titled “Research data management and sharing with the depositar, a research data repository”, the depositar team colaborated with Dr. Wen-Tzong Liang of the Institute of Earth Sciences and Prof. Tai-Lin Tseng to create an Earth Sciences project use case, the <a href="https://data.depositar.io/en/organization/armeniaseismicarray">Armenia Seismic Array</a>.</p> <p>This presentation also marks the first collaboration between our team and earth sciences scholars. During this collaboration, we had the opportunity to gain a deeper understanding of the considerations and needs for research data management and sharing in the field of earth sciences. For example, details such as the scale and diversity of Earth science research data as well as the need of dataset citation all provided us with a deeper insight into research data management practices.</p> <p>The presentation slide deck is made available on the <em>depositar</em> at <a href="https://pid.depositar.io/ark:37281/k5x825v5q">https://pid.depositar.io/ark:37281/k5x825v5q</a>.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/news/250213_title-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/news/250213_title-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/news/250213_title-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/news/250213_title.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption mt-0"> <b>Tyng-Ruey Chuang with the presentation title page. (Photo by James X. Morris, <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">CC BY-SA</a>)</b> </div> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/news/250213_example-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/news/250213_example-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/news/250213_example-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/news/250213_example.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption mt-0"> <b>The library space with the talk audience and the depositar team at the Institute of Earth Sciences with the projection screen showing the "Armenia Seismic Array" project. (Photo by ally, <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY</a>)</b> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On February 13, 2025, the depositar team was invited by the Institute of Earth Sciences at the Academia Sinica to share experience about research data management during their weekly Geotalk event.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The depositar lab is hiring!</title><link href="https://lab.depositar.io/news/241224_1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The depositar lab is hiring!"/><published>2024-12-24T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-12-24T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://lab.depositar.io/news/241224_1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lab.depositar.io/news/241224_1/"><![CDATA[<p>Please see the <a href="/zh-tw/news/241224_1/">announcement in Chinese</a> for details.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Please see the announcement in Chinese for details.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Wikidata Cross Domain Forum 2024 Lecture - Small-team Contemporary Archiving: Looking Back and Moving Forward</title><link href="https://lab.depositar.io/news/241218_1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wikidata Cross Domain Forum 2024 Lecture - Small-team Contemporary Archiving: Looking Back and Moving Forward"/><published>2024-12-18T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-12-18T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://lab.depositar.io/news/241218_1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lab.depositar.io/news/241218_1/"><![CDATA[<p>Please see the <a href="/zh-tw/news/241218_1/">announcement in Chinese</a> for details.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Please see the announcement in Chinese for details.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The depositar team invited to share research data management concepts and practices at the workshop hosted by the Taiwan Biodiversity Information Facility</title><link href="https://lab.depositar.io/news/241217_2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The depositar team invited to share research data management concepts and practices at the workshop hosted by the Taiwan Biodiversity Information Facility"/><published>2024-12-17T10:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-12-17T10:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://lab.depositar.io/news/241217_2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lab.depositar.io/news/241217_2/"><![CDATA[<p>The depositar team was invited by the Taiwan Biodiversity Information Facility (TaiBIF) at Academia Sinica to present on research data management (RDM), data management plans (DMPs), and open science at their workshop, <em>Biodiversity Data Publishing and Application Workshop</em>. The event, taken placed from Nov. 6 to Nov. 8, 2024, brought together individuals working with biological data and provided valuable guidance on organizing, publishing, and sharing data, highlighting the importance of open biodiversity data for both researchers and the wider community.</p> <p>In addition to introducing key concepts, our team led a session on reviewing data management plan examples from their field and demonstrated how RDM can be applied throughout a research project. Participants in the workshop also included those interested in TaiBIF’s volunteer training program, which aims to strengthen the community and promote best practices in data sharing. We are grateful for the opportunity to connect with life sciences researchers and hope that our session was valuable to them.</p> <p>The slide deck used in the presentation is available on the <em>depositar</em>: <a href="https://pid.depositar.io/ark:37281/k5f6m4q3h">ark:37281/k5f6m4q3h</a></p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/news/241217_2_ally_depositar-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/news/241217_2_ally_depositar-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/news/241217_2_ally_depositar-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/news/241217_2_ally_depositar.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/news/241217_2_hilary_rdm.svg" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/news/241217_2_hilary_rdm.svg" class="img-fluid rounded" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> <b>CC-BY Taiwan Biodiversity Information Facility (TaiBIF)</b> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The depositar team was invited by the Taiwan Biodiversity Information Facility (TaiBIF) at Academia Sinica to present on research data management (RDM), data management plans (DMPs), and open science at their workshop, Biodiversity Data Publishing and Application Workshop. The event, taken placed from Nov. 6 to Nov. 8, 2024, brought together individuals working with biological data and provided valuable guidance on organizing, publishing, and sharing data, highlighting the importance of open biodiversity data for both researchers and the wider community.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The depositar team shared experiences in the CKAN Monthly Live online meetup</title><link href="https://lab.depositar.io/news/241217_1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The depositar team shared experiences in the CKAN Monthly Live online meetup"/><published>2024-12-17T08:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-12-17T08:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://lab.depositar.io/news/241217_1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lab.depositar.io/news/241217_1/"><![CDATA[<p>The depositar team was invited to participate in the <a href="https://ckan.org/events/depositar-public-research-data-repository-built-on-ckan">CKAN Monthly Live online meetup</a> in November 2024 and gave a presentation titled <em>Depositar – A Public Research Data Repository Built on CKAN</em>, sharing our experiences over the past few years in building a research data repository on the CKAN platform. We also engaged in discussions with CKAN community partners and the technical team. Approximately 50 people attended the event.</p> <p>The slideset is at the depositar <a href="https://pid.depositar.io/ark:37281/k5r1c1v47">ark:37281/k5r1c1v47</a>, and the event recording will be edited and later released on the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@ckanassociation6525">CKAN Association YouTube channel</a>.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/news/241217_1-ckan-live-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/news/241217_1-ckan-live-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/news/241217_1-ckan-live-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/news/241217_1-ckan-live.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The depositar team was invited to participate in the CKAN Monthly Live online meetup in November 2024 and gave a presentation titled Depositar – A Public Research Data Repository Built on CKAN, sharing our experiences over the past few years in building a research data repository on the CKAN platform. We also engaged in discussions with CKAN community partners and the technical team. Approximately 50 people attended the event.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">National Taiwan Normal University Open Access Week Lecture - From data repository to research data management practice</title><link href="https://lab.depositar.io/news/241217_3/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="National Taiwan Normal University Open Access Week Lecture - From data repository to research data management practice"/><published>2024-12-17T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-12-17T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://lab.depositar.io/news/241217_3</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lab.depositar.io/news/241217_3/"><![CDATA[<p>Please see the <a href="/zh-tw/news/241217_3/">announcement in Chinese</a> for details.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Please see the announcement in Chinese for details.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Report on the 19th International Conference on Open Repositories (OR2024)</title><link href="https://lab.depositar.io/news/241203_1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Report on the 19th International Conference on Open Repositories (OR2024)"/><published>2024-12-03T14:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-12-03T14:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://lab.depositar.io/news/241203_1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lab.depositar.io/news/241203_1/"><![CDATA[<blockquote> <p>The <em>depositar</em> team attended the <em>19th International Conference on Open Repositories</em> (OR2024) in Göteborg, Sweden, on June 3–6, 2024. <a href="https://rdm.depositar.io/zh_TW/news/20241114-OR2024">Cheng-Jen Lee wrote a detailed report in Traditional Chinese</a>. Below is a report from Tyng-Ruey Chuang in English.</p> </blockquote> <p>The <a href="https://or2024.openrepositories.org/">19th International Conference on Open Repositories (OR2024)</a> was held in Göteborg, Sweden, on June 3–6, 2024. Eleven workshops took place on June 3. The main conference was held from June 4th to June 6th and it included keynotes, presentations, panels, DevTrack sessions, 24x7 (7-minute lightning talks with each comprising no more than 24 slides) as well as a repository showdown and a poster session. The conference, hosted by the Chamlers University of Technology, was very well organized. The conference venue was the Clarion Hotel Post in central Göteborg. In total, 425 people from 45 countries attended the conference.</p> <p>The OR2024 full program is available in <a href="https://www.conftool.net/or2024/sessions.php">ConfTool</a>. Slides from the contributors can be found in the <a href="https://zenodo.org/communities/openrepos/records?q=&amp;f=subject%3AOR2024">Open Repositories Community in Zenodo</a>. In the following, we highlight some of the sessions we attended. Due to limited space, this report can only be considered selective and subjective.</p> <p>In the <a href="https://www.conftool.net/or2024/index.php?page=browseSessions&amp;form_session=439&amp;presentations=show">Repositories Implementations</a> session, researchers from Stanford University, Harvard University, and a team in the Netherlands (Leiden University, DANS, CNR-ISTI/OpenAIRE, and Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam) shared their experience in the planning and migration of existing digital repositories to modern data infrastructures in order to meet new requirements and/or to accommodate unexpected changes. All three presentations offered valuable advice. In the <a href="https://www.conftool.net/or2024/index.php?page=browseSessions&amp;form_session=448&amp;presentations=show">Repository Rodeo</a> panel, representatives from several repository software and services (including Dataverse, DSpace, EPrints, Fedora, InvenioRDM, Islandora, and Samvera) all engaged with the audience with the directions of their respective technical and community developments.</p> <p>Cheng-Jen Lee, the tech lead of the <em><a href="https://data.depositar.io/about">depositar</a></em>, the data repository we have been developing in Academia Sinica, gave a presentation on <em><a href="https://pid.depositar.io/ark:37281/k5h2q5h19">Bringing Computation and Reproducibility to a Data Repository Using Binder</a></em> at the <a href="https://www.conftool.net/or2024/index.php?page=browseSessions&amp;form_session=519&amp;presentations=show">Developer Track Session 2</a>. In the presentation, he detailed how to extend <a href="https://binderhub.readthedocs.io/">BinderHub</a> (a Kubernetes-based package powering the Binder service) to CKAN (software for managing and publishing datasets, and from which the <em>depositar</em> is derived) so users can easily create and share executable computing environments from datasets in the repository. In the <a href="https://www.conftool.net/or2024/index.php?page=browseSessions&amp;form_session=529&amp;presentations=show">Data Repositories and Lessons Learned</a> session, <em>depositar</em> project lead Tyng-Ruey Chuang gave a presentation on <em><a href="https://pid.depositar.io/ark:37281/k5n4c2v0n">Building An Open Repository for FAIR Data: Experience Sharing on Technologies, Communities, and Policies</a></em>. He talked about the <em>depositar</em> team’s experience in community outreach and policy dialogue, in addition to the technical development of the open source data repository itself. The other presentations in the session were from Princeton University, KTH Royal Institute of Technology, and a consortium of research libraries in Canada. We feel the presenters all stress the importance of careful planning and long-term commitment of research institutions for the repositories they operate.</p> <p>In the <a href="https://www.conftool.net/or2024/index.php?page=browseSessions&amp;form_session=523&amp;presentations=show">24x7: Technical Solutions</a> session, we would like to highlight two enjoyable presentations from the Czech Republic. Hana Vyčítalová, Petra Černohlávková, and David Gerner from the National Library of Technology shared their experience in moving from Invenio 1 to DSpace 7. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.12548342">Their presentation is stunning</a>. Martin Lhotak, Filip Kersch, and Petr Zabicka (Library of the Czech Academy of Sciences and Moravian Library in Brno) presented <a href="https://old.starfos.tacr.cz/en/project/DH23P03OVV033">Orbis Pictus</a>: a project to open up the graphic content of digital libraries to the public, in particular about developing a tool to identify persons by their images in digitized books. The <a href="https://www.conftool.net/or2024/index.php?page=browseSessions&amp;form_session=522&amp;presentations=show">Trends and the Future of Open</a> session is an overview of the research data landscape in Europe (but the observations are applicable elsewhere in the world). We recommend the readers to look into <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.12579359">the presentation from Richard David Jones</a> (Cottage Labs) where he reflected on his involvement in Open Access for the last 25 years. He provided insightful perspective on the current and future roles of repositories in improving global publishing equity.</p> <p>We wish to note we finally met John Kunze after corresponding with him for several years. He and Donny Winston organized a workshop on <a href="https://www.conftool.net/or2024/index.php?page=browseSessions&amp;form_session=496&amp;presentations=show">Getting Running with ARK Persistent Identifiers</a>. Using Archival Resource Key (ARK), the <em>depositar</em> team has developed <a href="https://github.com/depositar/ckanext-ark">a CKAN extension</a> for <a href="https://docs.depositar.io/en/stable/user-guide/ark-identifier.html">assigning persistent identifiers (PIDs) to datasets</a>. It is joyful to be able to meet, in person, the people who have helped us so much.</p> <p><a href="https://or2025.openrepositories.org/">The 20th International Conference on Open Repositories (OR2025)</a> will take place on June 15–18, 2025, in Chicago, Illinois, USA. The theme for the OR2025 conference is <em>Twenty Years of Progress, a Future of Possibilities</em>. The <a href="https://or2025.openrepositories.org/program/call-for-proposals/">Call for Proposals</a> is now open with a submission deadline of December 18, 2024.</p> <p>Our travels to attend the conference have been supported by the Institute of Information Science, Academia Sinica, and by the National Science and Technology Council of Taiwan.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/news/repository-rodeo_or2024.JPG" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/news/repository-rodeo_or2024.JPG" class="img-thumbnail" width="100%" height="auto" alt="Q&amp;A at the Repository Rodeo session, OR2024. Photo: Tyng-Ruey Chuang" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> <b>Q&amp;A at the Repository Rodeo session, OR2024. Photo: Tyng-Ruey Chuang.</b> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The depositar team attended the 19th International Conference on Open Repositories (OR2024) in Göteborg, Sweden, on June 3–6, 2024. Cheng-Jen Lee wrote a detailed report in Traditional Chinese. Below is a report from Tyng-Ruey Chuang in English.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Report on the Computational Social Science Conference, 28-29 October 2024, Barcelona</title><link href="https://lab.depositar.io/news/241115_1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Report on the Computational Social Science Conference, 28-29 October 2024, Barcelona"/><published>2024-11-15T06:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-11-15T06:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://lab.depositar.io/news/241115_1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lab.depositar.io/news/241115_1/"><![CDATA[<blockquote> <p>Tyng-Ruey Chuang recently attended a CODATA Executive Committee meeting in Barcelona and, proceeding it, the Computational Social Science Conference hosted by the Barcelona Supercomputing Center.</p> </blockquote> <p>Organized by the <a href="https://www.bsc.es/">Barcelona Supercomputing Center (BSC)</a>, <a href="https://codata.org/about-codata/">CODATA</a> and <a href="https://lacaixafoundation.org/en/">Fundació La Caixa</a>, the <em><a href="https://codata.org/events/conferences/computational-social-science-conference-2024/">Computational Social Science Conference: Innovative Methods, Research Workflows and Data Stewardship</a></em> was held on 28-29 October, 2024, in Barcelona at the campus of <a href="https://www.upc.edu/en/the-upc/the-institution">Universitat Politècnica de Catalunya (UPC)</a>. The conference is consisted of five sessions on the intertwined topics of data sciences and social sciences, with a lively lightning talks session, and starting with a keynote by David Lazer on <em>Building a Trans-Atlantic Coalition for Studying the Giants of the Internet</em>. The conference, overall, has been an intense two-day meeting with <a href="https://codata.org/events/conferences/computational-social-science-conference-2024/speakers-and-abstracts/">speakers giving expert overviews of the challenging issues faced and addressed by front-line social science researchers</a>. By our estimates, the conference was attended by about 150 researchers and students, with around a quarter of them traveling from abroad for the meeting.</p> <p>In his keynote, David Lazer (Northeastern University) talks about the problems in relying on social media platforms (e.g. the site formally known as Twitter) for human behavior data when doing academic research. He advocates instead a shared research infrastructure with voluntarily contributed user data, as exemplified by the <a href="https://nationalinternetobservatory.org/">National Internet Observatory</a> project funded by the National Science Foundation in the US. In the following, we then highlight some of the other talks given in the conference. Note that this report is not meant to be comprehensive and, due to limited space, can only be considered selective and subjective. Slides from some of the presentations can be found at the conference website.</p> <p>In the first session, Chico Camargo (University of Exeter) surveys the areas in which complexity scientists can work in the social sciences (among them, “social data science” and “cultural evolution and cultural analytics”) and emphasizes the interdisciplinarity of works. Marga Torre (Universidad Carlos III de Madrid, UC3M) reflects on the successful establishment of a Master degree program in Computational Social Science at UC3M and its future challenges (among them, “interdisciplinarity for real” and “strengthen collaboration between social scientists and computer scientists”). David Garcia (University of Konstanz) talks about simulating opinion dynamics among LLM agents with some implications in decision-making.</p> <p>The second session is about data modeling for social science with contributions from Hannes Mueller (Barcelona School of Economics), Shaily Gandhi (University of Salzburg), and Sebastian Poledna (International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis). The topics ranged from ethics in economic forecast and policy making, enhancing disaster response with social media analytics, to economic modeling by large-scale simulations. The session is followed by lightning talks of which we are especially impressed by a presentation on the Living Arrangements Project, a world-scale multilevel analysis on household composition and change. The presentation is given by Paolo Marangio and Nienke Visscher (BSC).</p> <p>The second day of the conference starts with a session with two presentations on the state-of-art practices in research data repositories. Stefano Iacus (Harvard University) updates the audience on the recent advances in the Dataverse Project and on how to use differential privacy to improve access to sensitive data while maintaining confidentiality. Darren Bell (UK Data Service) detailed the real-world issues in mediating access to data objects stored in research data repositories (among them, costly human mediation, unstructured access policies, and the lack of upstream access metadata).</p> <p>The fourth session is on data description for AI and machine analysis. Gyorgy Gyomai (OECD) explores how <a href="https://sdmx.org/">SDMX (Statistical Data and Metadata eXchange)</a>, a standard to improve data connectivity and machine readability, can be an enabler for AI applications. Elena Simperl (King’s College London) give an engaging presentation on <a href="http://mlcommons.org/croissant/1.0">Croissant</a>, a community-driven metadata format for AI-ready datasets. Christine Kirkpatrick (San Diego Supercomputer Center) overviews the works being carried out in research networks such as <a href="https://www.farr-rcn.org/">FARR (FAIR in ML, AI Readiness, and Reproducibility)</a> and <a href="https://fairdo.org/">FAIR Digital Objects (FDOs)</a>.</p> <p>Data provenance and research reproducibility is the subject of the last session of the conference. Tony Ross-Hellauer (Know Center Research) presents the <a href="https://tier2-project.eu/">TIER2 Project</a>, funded by the European Union’s Horizon research programme, and discusses reproducibility challenges in computational social science. Carole Goble (University of Manchester) introduces the <a href="https://www.researchobject.org/ro-crate/">RO-Crate (Research Object Crate)</a> FAIR Digital Object framework for reproducible computational processing. Rosa Badia (BSC) provides an overview of <a href="https://pypi.org/project/pycompss/">PyCOMPSs</a>, a programming environment for the development of workflow applications, as well as on how it can be used to support computational reproducibility in high-performance computing. This session is probably the most technical one of the entire conference. It is nevertheless very enjoyable for people, like us, with a background in Computer Science.</p> <p>The conference organizers also arranged a visit to <a href="https://www.bsc.es/marenostrum/marenostrum-5">MareNostrum 5</a>, an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/European_High-Performance_Computing_Joint_Undertaking">EuroHPC Joint Undertaking</a> supercomputer hosted at BSC. The MareNostrum 5 ACC (Accelerated Partition) has 1120 nodes with each equipped with two Intel 40-core CPUs and four Nvidia Hopper GPUs. The cluster has a peak performance of 260 PFlops</p> <p>We thank <a href="https://www.bsc.es/news/bsc-news/merc%C3%A8-crosas-elected-new-president-the-committee-data-the-international-science-council">Dr. Mercè Crosas</a> (CODATA President and the head of Computational Social Sciences at BSC) for the invitation to participate in this exciting conference. Our travel to attend the meetings has been supported by CODATA and the Institute of Information Science, Academia Sinica, Taiwan.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/news/Computational_Social_Science_UPC_20241029.JPG" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/news/Computational_Social_Science_UPC_20241029.JPG" class="img-fluid rounded" width="100%" height="auto" alt="Universitat Politècnica de Catalunya (UPC). Photo: Tyng-Ruey Chuang." loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> <b>Universitat Politècnica de Catalunya (UPC). Photo: Tyng-Ruey Chuang.</b> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Tyng-Ruey Chuang recently attended a CODATA Executive Committee meeting in Barcelona and, proceeding it, the Computational Social Science Conference hosted by the Barcelona Supercomputing Center.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">depositar Syetem Update: Source Code Updated to Version v6.7.0</title><link href="https://lab.depositar.io/news/240830_1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="depositar Syetem Update: Source Code Updated to Version v6.7.0"/><published>2024-08-30T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-08-30T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://lab.depositar.io/news/240830_1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lab.depositar.io/news/240830_1/"><![CDATA[<p>The depositar system <a href="https://docs.depositar.io/en/stable/changelog.html#v6-7-0-2024-07-18">had been updated</a>! Please refer to <a href="https://lab.depositar.io/zh-tw/news/240830_1/">this post (in Mandarin)</a> for details.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The depositar system had been updated! Please refer to this post (in Mandarin) for details.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome, 2024 Summer Interns!</title><link href="https://lab.depositar.io/news/240702_1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome, 2024 Summer Interns!"/><published>2024-07-02T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-07-02T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://lab.depositar.io/news/240702_1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lab.depositar.io/news/240702_1/"><![CDATA[<p>We welcome five intern students to the depositar lab this summer! As part of the internship training, we organize short courses on <a href="https://rdm.depositar.io/">Research Data Management (RDM)</a>, structured text, git, and Jupyter Book (<a href="https://lab.depositar.io/zh-tw/news/240304_1/">see last year’s intern projects</a>), <a href="https://qgis.org/">QGIS</a>, <a href="https://www.openstreetmap.org/">OpenStreetMap</a>, <a href="https://www.wikidata.org">Wikidata</a>, and 360° photo/video documentation and processing:</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th>Course</th> <th>Instructor</th> <th>Date &amp; Time</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>RDM &amp; <em>depositar</em></td> <td>Chia-Hsun Ally Wang &amp; Ming-Syuan Ho</td> <td>July 2, 10:00 am</td> </tr> <tr> <td>git &amp; Jupyter Book</td> <td>Cheng-Jen Lee</td> <td>July 9, 10:00 am</td> </tr> <tr> <td>QGIS</td> <td>Hsiung-Ming Liao</td> <td>July 16, 10:00 am</td> </tr> <tr> <td>OpenStreetMap</td> <td>Dennis Raylin Chen</td> <td>July 17, 10:00 am</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Wikidata</td> <td>Dennis Raylin Chen</td> <td>July 24, 10:00 am</td> </tr> <tr> <td>360° photos/videos</td> <td>Yu-Huang Wang</td> <td>July 25, 10:00 am</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p><br/></p> <p>By giving these short courses, we hope to introduce the students to the basics of research data management and static website generation, as well as to the use and enrichment of communal resources of open geographic information and structured data. The courses will be held at the Institute of Information Science, Academia Sinica, and conducted in Taiwanese Mandarin. After taking these courses, the interns will work on personal projects.</p> <p>We are especially grateful to our guest lecturers: Hsiung-Ming Liao (GIS Center, RCHSS, Academia Sinica), Yu-Huang Wang (Nature Watch Ecological and Environmental Consultancy), and Dennis Raylin Chen (Wikimedia Taiwan).</p> <p>This year the summer internship students are from the National Cheng Kung University, the National Chung Cheng University, and the National Dong Hwa University in Taiwan, and from Vassar College in New York, USA.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We welcome five intern students to the depositar lab this summer! As part of the internship training, we organize short courses on Research Data Management (RDM), structured text, git, and Jupyter Book (see last year’s intern projects), QGIS, OpenStreetMap, Wikidata, and 360° photo/video documentation and processing:]]></summary></entry></feed>