<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://depositar.github.io/feed/news.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://depositar.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-03-31T04:22:06+00:00</updated><id>https://depositar.github.io/feed/news.xml</id><title type="html">depositar lab | News</title><subtitle>The website of the depositar lab. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">news.titles.240325-1</title><link href="https://depositar.github.io/news/240325_1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="news.titles.240325-1"/><published>2024-03-25T02:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-25T02:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://depositar.github.io/news/240325_1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://depositar.github.io/news/240325_1/"><![CDATA[<p>Tyng-Ruey Chuang reported on the developments in the US and Taiwan about the public’s access to the output of federal/national scientific research. This article was simultaneously published in the <a href="https://rdm.depositar.io/zh_TW/news/20231115-us-taiwan-recent-public-access-development">Research Data Management Hub (RDM Hub)</a> and the <a href="https://www.scimonth.com.tw/archives/7684">SciTech Report</a> in November 2023.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/news/SciReport_2023-11-15_p1-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/news/SciReport_2023-11-15_p1-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/news/SciReport_2023-11-15_p1-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/news/SciReport_2023-11-15_p1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded" width="auto" height="auto" alt="SciReport Screenshot 2023-11-15" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> <b>Public Access to Government-funded Research</b> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Tyng-Ruey Chuang reported on the developments in the US and Taiwan about the public’s access to the output of federal/national scientific research. This article was simultaneously published in the Research Data Management Hub (RDM Hub) and the SciTech Report in November 2023. Public Access to Government-funded Research]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">news.titles.240304-1</title><link href="https://depositar.github.io/news/240304_1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="news.titles.240304-1"/><published>2024-03-04T03:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-04T03:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://depositar.github.io/news/240304_1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://depositar.github.io/news/240304_1/"><![CDATA[<p>2024 Summer Internship Program! Please see the <a href="/zh-tw/news/240304_1/">announcement in Chinese</a> for details.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[2024 Summer Internship Program! Please see the announcement in Chinese for details.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">news.titles.230905-1</title><link href="https://depositar.github.io/news/230905_1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="news.titles.230905-1"/><published>2023-09-05T03:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-09-05T03:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://depositar.github.io/news/230905_1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://depositar.github.io/news/230905_1/"><![CDATA[<p>At the invitation of the Office of Academic Integrity Promotion at National Cheng Kung University (NCKU), Ho Ming-Syuan will be delivering a lecture titled “From data repository to research data management practice” on September 19, 2023. The event will be conducted online, and anyone can register.</p> <h3 id="introduction-and-registration-link-for-nckus-office-of-academic-integrity-promotion">Introduction and Registration Link for NCKU’s Office of Academic Integrity Promotion</h3> <p><a href="https://oai.web2.ncku.edu.tw/p/406-1072-212237,r164.php?Lang=zh-tw">https://oai.web2.ncku.edu.tw/p/406-1072-212237,r164.php?Lang=zh-tw</a></p> <p><img src="https://oai.web2.ncku.edu.tw/var/file/72/1072/img/9.png" height="700px"/></p> <h3 id="lecture-description">Lecture Description</h3> <p>“As operators of research data repositories, what aspects should we consider to effectively assist researchers?” This is a question often pondered by depositar team members during the development and research process.</p> <p>To ensure the reproducibility of academic research and enhance the efficiency of scientific research, an increasing number of research funding agencies and journals now require researchers to establish how their research data will be made accessible at specific times, such as by depositing it in publicly accessible research data repositories. Additionally, many research teams are required to submit a “Data Management Plan” at the beginning of their research projects, detailing the methods for collecting, recording, managing, and preserving research data during the project’s implementation, as well as ongoing data management as described in the plan.</p> <p>This lecture will start from the perspective of research data repository operators and explain how research data repositories can assist researchers in data management. It will cover fundamental concepts of research data management, the formulation of data management plans, and developments in international policies related to open science.</p> <h3 id="slides-link">Slides Link</h3> <p><a href="https://data.depositar.io/dataset/2023-09-19_ncku-academic-integrity-lectrue_depositar-and-rdm">https://data.depositar.io/dataset/2023-09-19_ncku-academic-integrity-lectrue_depositar-and-rdm</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[At the invitation of the Office of Academic Integrity Promotion at National Cheng Kung University (NCKU), Ho Ming-Syuan will be delivering a lecture titled “From data repository to research data management practice” on September 19, 2023. The event will be conducted online, and anyone can register. Introduction and Registration Link for NCKU’s Office of Academic Integrity Promotion https://oai.web2.ncku.edu.tw/p/406-1072-212237,r164.php?Lang=zh-tw Lecture Description “As operators of research data repositories, what aspects should we consider to effectively assist researchers?” This is a question often pondered by depositar team members during the development and research process. To ensure the reproducibility of academic research and enhance the efficiency of scientific research, an increasing number of research funding agencies and journals now require researchers to establish how their research data will be made accessible at specific times, such as by depositing it in publicly accessible research data repositories. Additionally, many research teams are required to submit a “Data Management Plan” at the beginning of their research projects, detailing the methods for collecting, recording, managing, and preserving research data during the project’s implementation, as well as ongoing data management as described in the plan. This lecture will start from the perspective of research data repository operators and explain how research data repositories can assist researchers in data management. It will cover fundamental concepts of research data management, the formulation of data management plans, and developments in international policies related to open science. Slides Link https://data.depositar.io/dataset/2023-09-19_ncku-academic-integrity-lectrue_depositar-and-rdm]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">news.titles.230725-1</title><link href="https://depositar.github.io/news/230725_1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="news.titles.230725-1"/><published>2023-07-25T04:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-25T04:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://depositar.github.io/news/230725_1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://depositar.github.io/news/230725_1/"><![CDATA[<p>Cheng-Jen Lee attended the <a href="https://or2023.openrepositories.org/">Open Repositories 2023</a> (OR2023) conference on June 12-15, 2023, in Cape Town, South Africa. He presented the recently developed <a href="https://docs.depositar.io/en/stable/user-guide.html#ark-identifier">ARK persistent identifier</a> scheme for the depositar. The slides for the presentation, <em>A Persistent Identifier Practice For A Research Data Repository</em>, can be found at <a href="https://n2t.net/ark:37281/k562n4m0z">https://n2t.net/ark:37281/k562n4m0z</a>.</p> <p>For details, please refer to this article (<a href="/zh-tw/news/230725_1/">in Chinese</a>). The article is adapted from the conference report prepared by Cheng-Jen Lee and submitted to Academia Sinica.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Cheng-Jen Lee attended the Open Repositories 2023 (OR2023) conference on June 12-15, 2023, in Cape Town, South Africa. He presented the recently developed ARK persistent identifier scheme for the depositar. The slides for the presentation, A Persistent Identifier Practice For A Research Data Repository, can be found at https://n2t.net/ark:37281/k562n4m0z. For details, please refer to this article (in Chinese). The article is adapted from the conference report prepared by Cheng-Jen Lee and submitted to Academia Sinica.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">news.titles.230720-1</title><link href="https://depositar.github.io/news/230720_1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="news.titles.230720-1"/><published>2023-07-20T03:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-20T03:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://depositar.github.io/news/230720_1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://depositar.github.io/news/230720_1/"><![CDATA[<p>A few major research organiations have recently formulated or updated their data sharing policies. Data sharing is increasingly viewed as a responsibility of the global scientific community. In his article, titled “Making Data Sharing a Responsibility: On Recent Open Research Data Policies”, Ming-Syuan Ho reviews the data sharing policies of the World Health Organization (WHO), the European Organization for Nuclear Research (CERN), and the U.S. National Institutes of Health (NIH), as well as the challenges these policies may face. This article is simultaneously published in the <a href="https://rdm.depositar.io/zh_TW/news/20220719-international-data-sharing-polices">Research Data Management Hub (RDM Hub)</a> and the <a href="https://www.scimonth.com.tw/archives/6512">SciTech Report</a> in July.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/news/p_1_2023-07-15_SciTech_Report-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/news/p_1_2023-07-15_SciTech_Report-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/news/p_1_2023-07-15_SciTech_Report-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/news/p_1_2023-07-15_SciTech_Report.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" alt="Data sharing a responsibility of research organizations" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> <b>Data Sharing A Responsibility</b> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A few major research organiations have recently formulated or updated their data sharing policies. Data sharing is increasingly viewed as a responsibility of the global scientific community. In his article, titled “Making Data Sharing a Responsibility: On Recent Open Research Data Policies”, Ming-Syuan Ho reviews the data sharing policies of the World Health Organization (WHO), the European Organization for Nuclear Research (CERN), and the U.S. National Institutes of Health (NIH), as well as the challenges these policies may face. This article is simultaneously published in the Research Data Management Hub (RDM Hub) and the SciTech Report in July. Data Sharing A Responsibility]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">news.titles.230711-1</title><link href="https://depositar.github.io/news/230711_1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="news.titles.230711-1"/><published>2023-07-11T04:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-11T04:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://depositar.github.io/news/230711_1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://depositar.github.io/news/230711_1/"><![CDATA[<p>This year the depositar lab welcomes eight summer internship students! As part of the training, we will hold short courses for the interns on <a href="https://qgis.org/">QGIS</a>, <a href="https://qfield.org/">QField</a>, <a href="https://www.openstreetmap.org/">OpenStreetMap</a>, and <a href="https://www.wikidata.org">Wikidata</a>:</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th>Course</th> <th>Instructor</th> <th>Date &amp; Time</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>QGIS</td> <td>Hsiung-Ming Liao</td> <td>July 18, 2:00pm – 4:30pm</td> </tr> <tr> <td>QField</td> <td>Yu-Huang Wang</td> <td>July 20, 10:00am - 12:30pm</td> </tr> <tr> <td>OpenStreetMap</td> <td>Dennis Raylin Chen</td> <td>July 26, 10:00am - 12:30pm</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Wikidata</td> <td>Dennis Raylin Chen</td> <td>July 27, 10:00am - 12:30pm</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p><br/></p> <p>By giving these short courses, we hope to introduce the students to the use and enrichment of these communal resources of open geographic information and structured data. The courses will be held in room <del>N107</del> N106 at the Institute of Information Science, Academia Sinica, and conducted in Taiwanese Mandarin.</p> <p>We thank Hsiung-Ming Liao (GIS Center, RCHSS, Academia Sinica), Yu-Huang Wang (Nature Watch Ecological and Environmental Consultancy), and Dennis Raylin Chen (Wikimedia Taiwan) for teaching the courses.</p> <p>This year the summer internship students are from the CCU, NTHU, NTNU, NTU, NYCU, and Yunlin Tech in Taiwan, and from Georgia Tech and Texas A&amp;M in the US.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This year the depositar lab welcomes eight summer internship students! As part of the training, we will hold short courses for the interns on QGIS, QField, OpenStreetMap, and Wikidata: Course Instructor Date &amp; Time QGIS Hsiung-Ming Liao July 18, 2:00pm – 4:30pm QField Yu-Huang Wang July 20, 10:00am - 12:30pm OpenStreetMap Dennis Raylin Chen July 26, 10:00am - 12:30pm Wikidata Dennis Raylin Chen July 27, 10:00am - 12:30pm By giving these short courses, we hope to introduce the students to the use and enrichment of these communal resources of open geographic information and structured data. The courses will be held in room N107 N106 at the Institute of Information Science, Academia Sinica, and conducted in Taiwanese Mandarin. We thank Hsiung-Ming Liao (GIS Center, RCHSS, Academia Sinica), Yu-Huang Wang (Nature Watch Ecological and Environmental Consultancy), and Dennis Raylin Chen (Wikimedia Taiwan) for teaching the courses. This year the summer internship students are from the CCU, NTHU, NTNU, NTU, NYCU, and Yunlin Tech in Taiwan, and from Georgia Tech and Texas A&amp;M in the US.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">news.titles.230709-1</title><link href="https://depositar.github.io/news/230709_1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="news.titles.230709-1"/><published>2023-07-09T04:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-09T04:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://depositar.github.io/news/230709_1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://depositar.github.io/news/230709_1/"><![CDATA[<p>On June 26, the depositar team visited the <a href="https://www.nchc.org.tw/">National Center for High-Performance Computing (NCHC)</a> in Hsinchu. Tyng-Ruey Chuang, Cheng-Jen Lee, and Chia-Hsun Ally Wang gave <a href="https://m.odw.tw/u/trc/m/what-is-the-depositar/">an overview of the depositar project</a> and introduced <a href="https://m.odw.tw/u/odw/m/2023-nchc-an-introduction-to-depositar/">the services provided by the depositar</a>. Researchers from NCHC’s Data Science and Technology Division presented the <a href="https://scidm.nchc.org.tw/">data market platform</a> and other data services hosted at NCHC. At the meeting, the two teams discussed several potential directions for future collaboration. The meeting was initiated and arranged by <a href="https://codata.sinica.edu.tw/">CODATA Taiwan</a>.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/news/What_is_the_depositar_2023-06-26_NCHC_p_1-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/news/What_is_the_depositar_2023-06-26_NCHC_p_1-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/news/What_is_the_depositar_2023-06-26_NCHC_p_1-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/news/What_is_the_depositar_2023-06-26_NCHC_p_1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" alt="What is the depositar?&lt;" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> <b>What is the <em>depositar</em>?</b> </div> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/news/2023-06-26_NCHC_an_introduction_to_depositar_p_1-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/news/2023-06-26_NCHC_an_introduction_to_depositar_p_1-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/news/2023-06-26_NCHC_an_introduction_to_depositar_p_1-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/news/2023-06-26_NCHC_an_introduction_to_depositar_p_1.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" alt="An Introduction to depositar" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> <b>An Introduction to <em>depositar</em></b> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On June 26, the depositar team visited the National Center for High-Performance Computing (NCHC) in Hsinchu. Tyng-Ruey Chuang, Cheng-Jen Lee, and Chia-Hsun Ally Wang gave an overview of the depositar project and introduced the services provided by the depositar. Researchers from NCHC’s Data Science and Technology Division presented the data market platform and other data services hosted at NCHC. At the meeting, the two teams discussed several potential directions for future collaboration. The meeting was initiated and arranged by CODATA Taiwan. What is the depositar? An Introduction to depositar]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">news.titles.230703-1</title><link href="https://depositar.github.io/news/230703_1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="news.titles.230703-1"/><published>2023-07-03T04:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-03T04:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://depositar.github.io/news/230703_1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://depositar.github.io/news/230703_1/"><![CDATA[<p>At the invitation of the organizers, we participated in the <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/ecological-informatics/">Ecological Informatics Mini-Symposium</a> on June 11, 2023. Tyng-Ruey Chuang gave a 20-min talk on <em><a href="https://m.odw.tw/u/trc/m/ltser-data-strategy/">Thoughts on Long-Term Socio-Ecological Research (LTSER) Data Management and Preservation</a></em>. Materials in some part of the presentation slides come from <a href="https://rdm.depositar.io/resources/20221007-LTSER-data-managment-principles">a blog post by Paopei Huang at the Research Data Management Hub</a>.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/news/2023-06-11_ecological-informatics_1-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/news/2023-06-11_ecological-informatics_1-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/news/2023-06-11_ecological-informatics_1-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/news/2023-06-11_ecological-informatics_1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" alt="Thoughts on Long-Term Socio-Ecological Research (LTSER) Data Management and Preservation" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> <b>Thoughts on Long-Term Socio-Ecological Research (LTSER) Data Management and Preservation</b> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[At the invitation of the organizers, we participated in the Ecological Informatics Mini-Symposium on June 11, 2023. Tyng-Ruey Chuang gave a 20-min talk on Thoughts on Long-Term Socio-Ecological Research (LTSER) Data Management and Preservation. Materials in some part of the presentation slides come from a blog post by Paopei Huang at the Research Data Management Hub. Thoughts on Long-Term Socio-Ecological Research (LTSER) Data Management and Preservation]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">news.titles.230630-1</title><link href="https://depositar.github.io/news/230630_1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="news.titles.230630-1"/><published>2023-06-30T04:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-30T04:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://depositar.github.io/news/230630_1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://depositar.github.io/news/230630_1/"><![CDATA[<p>Invited by the <a href="http://www.fhccr.org.tw/">Foundation of Historic City Conservation and Regeneration</a>, we participated in the <a href="https://artouch.com/art-views/cultural-policy/content-110719.html">“Taiwan’s 400th anniversary, and then?”</a> forum on June 4, 2023. Tyng-Ruey Chuang gave a 20-min talk on <em><a href="https://m.odw.tw/u/trc/m/tainan-400-talk/">Open Repositories for Landscape Documentations</a></em>. The slides for the talk were modified from those that were previously used in the <a href="https://pid.depositar.io/ark:37281/k5z9s6309">2021 Workshop on Cultural and Natural Landscape Documentation</a>.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/news/2023_Landscape_Doc-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/news/2023_Landscape_Doc-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/news/2023_Landscape_Doc-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/news/2023_Landscape_Doc.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" alt="Open Repositories for Landscape Documentations" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> <b>Open Repositories for Landscape Documentations</b> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Invited by the Foundation of Historic City Conservation and Regeneration, we participated in the “Taiwan’s 400th anniversary, and then?” forum on June 4, 2023. Tyng-Ruey Chuang gave a 20-min talk on Open Repositories for Landscape Documentations. The slides for the talk were modified from those that were previously used in the 2021 Workshop on Cultural and Natural Landscape Documentation. Open Repositories for Landscape Documentations]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">news.titles.230505-1</title><link href="https://depositar.github.io/news/230505_1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="news.titles.230505-1"/><published>2023-05-05T04:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-05T04:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://depositar.github.io/news/230505_1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://depositar.github.io/news/230505_1/"><![CDATA[<p>In January, the depositar lab visited the <a href="https://www.cires-taiwan.org/">Center for Interdisciplinary Research on Ecology and Sustainability (CIRES)</a> at the National Dong Hwa University to exchange ideas and practices on research data management (RDM). Paopei Huang wrote a report about the visit. This article, which is in Chinese, is now online at <a href="https://rdm.depositar.io/showcases/20230427-CIRES-depositar-communication">RDM Hub (研究資料管理推進室)</a> and will be published by <a href="https://www.scimonth.com.tw/archives/6388"><em>SciTech Report</em> (科技報導)</a> in May. The slides used in the meeting have been collected into a dataset: <a href="https://pid.depositar.io/ark:37281/k5v7d5f9c">ark:37281/k5v7d5f9c</a>.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/news/p_1_2023-05-15_SciTech_Report-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/news/p_1_2023-05-15_SciTech_Report-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/news/p_1_2023-05-15_SciTech_Report-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/news/p_1_2023-05-15_SciTech_Report.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" alt="Reporting on a visit to CIRES by the depositar team" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> <b>Reporting on a visit to CIRES by the depositar team</b> </div> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/news/depositar_visited_CIRES-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/news/depositar_visited_CIRES-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/news/depositar_visited_CIRES-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/news/depositar_visited_CIRES.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" alt="The depositar team visited CIRES at Dong Hwa Univ." onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> <b>The depositar team visited CIRES at Dong Hwa Univ.</b> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In January, the depositar lab visited the Center for Interdisciplinary Research on Ecology and Sustainability (CIRES) at the National Dong Hwa University to exchange ideas and practices on research data management (RDM). Paopei Huang wrote a report about the visit. This article, which is in Chinese, is now online at RDM Hub (研究資料管理推進室) and will be published by SciTech Report (科技報導) in May. The slides used in the meeting have been collected into a dataset: ark:37281/k5v7d5f9c. Reporting on a visit to CIRES by the depositar team The depositar team visited CIRES at Dong Hwa Univ.]]></summary></entry></feed>