<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://lab.depositar.io/feed/news.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://lab.depositar.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><updated>2024-12-18T10:02:12+08:00</updated><id>https://lab.depositar.io/feed/news.xml</id><title type="html">depositar lab | News</title><subtitle>The website of the depositar lab. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">The depositar team invited to share research data management concepts and practices at the workshop hosted by the Taiwan Biodiversity Information Facility</title><link href="https://lab.depositar.io/news/241217_2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The depositar team invited to share research data management concepts and practices at the workshop hosted by the Taiwan Biodiversity Information Facility"/><published>2024-12-17T10:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-12-17T10:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://lab.depositar.io/news/241217_2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lab.depositar.io/news/241217_2/"><![CDATA[<p>The depositar team was invited by the Taiwan Biodiversity Information Facility (TaiBIF) at Academia Sinica to present on research data management (RDM), data management plans (DMPs), and open science at their workshop, <em>Biodiversity Data Publishing and Application Workshop</em>. The event, taken placed from Nov. 6 to Nov. 8, 2024, brought together individuals working with biological data and provided valuable guidance on organizing, publishing, and sharing data, highlighting the importance of open biodiversity data for both researchers and the wider community.</p> <p>In addition to introducing key concepts, our team led a session on reviewing data management plan examples from their field and demonstrated how RDM can be applied throughout a research project. Participants in the workshop also included those interested in TaiBIF’s volunteer training program, which aims to strengthen the community and promote best practices in data sharing. We are grateful for the opportunity to connect with life sciences researchers and hope that our session was valuable to them.</p> <p>The slide deck used in the presentation is available on the <em>depositar</em>: <a href="https://pid.depositar.io/ark:37281/k5f6m4q3h">ark:37281/k5f6m4q3h</a></p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/news/241217_2_ally_depositar-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/news/241217_2_ally_depositar-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/news/241217_2_ally_depositar-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/news/241217_2_ally_depositar.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/news/241217_2_hilary_rdm.svg" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/news/241217_2_hilary_rdm.svg" class="img-fluid rounded" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> <b>CC-BY Taiwan Biodiversity Information Facility (TaiBIF)</b> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The depositar team was invited by the Taiwan Biodiversity Information Facility (TaiBIF) at Academia Sinica to present on research data management (RDM), data management plans (DMPs), and open science at their workshop, Biodiversity Data Publishing and Application Workshop. The event, taken placed from Nov. 6 to Nov. 8, 2024, brought together individuals working with biological data and provided valuable guidance on organizing, publishing, and sharing data, highlighting the importance of open biodiversity data for both researchers and the wider community.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The depositar team shared experiences in the CKAN Monthly Live online meetup</title><link href="https://lab.depositar.io/news/241217_1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The depositar team shared experiences in the CKAN Monthly Live online meetup"/><published>2024-12-17T08:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-12-17T08:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://lab.depositar.io/news/241217_1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lab.depositar.io/news/241217_1/"><![CDATA[<p>The depositar team was invited to participate in the <a href="https://ckan.org/events/depositar-public-research-data-repository-built-on-ckan">CKAN Monthly Live online meetup</a> in November 2024 and gave a presentation titled <em>Depositar – A Public Research Data Repository Built on CKAN</em>, sharing our experiences over the past few years in building a research data repository on the CKAN platform. We also engaged in discussions with CKAN community partners and the technical team. Approximately 50 people attended the event.</p> <p>The slideset is at the depositar <a href="https://pid.depositar.io/ark:37281/k5r1c1v47">ark:37281/k5r1c1v47</a>, and the event recording will be edited and later released on the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@ckanassociation6525">CKAN Association YouTube channel</a>.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/news/241217_1-ckan-live-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/news/241217_1-ckan-live-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/news/241217_1-ckan-live-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/news/241217_1-ckan-live.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The depositar team was invited to participate in the CKAN Monthly Live online meetup in November 2024 and gave a presentation titled Depositar – A Public Research Data Repository Built on CKAN, sharing our experiences over the past few years in building a research data repository on the CKAN platform. We also engaged in discussions with CKAN community partners and the technical team. Approximately 50 people attended the event.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Report on the 19th International Conference on Open Repositories (OR2024)</title><link href="https://lab.depositar.io/news/241203_1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Report on the 19th International Conference on Open Repositories (OR2024)"/><published>2024-12-03T14:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-12-03T14:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://lab.depositar.io/news/241203_1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lab.depositar.io/news/241203_1/"><![CDATA[<blockquote> <p>The <em>depositar</em> team attended the <em>19th International Conference on Open Repositories</em> (OR2024) in Göteborg, Sweden, on June 3–6, 2024. <a href="https://rdm.depositar.io/zh_TW/news/20241114-OR2024">Cheng-Jen Lee wrote a detailed report in Traditional Chinese</a>. Below is a report from Tyng-Ruey Chuang in English.</p> </blockquote> <p>The <a href="https://or2024.openrepositories.org/">19th International Conference on Open Repositories (OR2024)</a> was held in Göteborg, Sweden, on June 3–6, 2024. Eleven workshops took place on June 3. The main conference was held from June 4th to June 6th and it included keynotes, presentations, panels, DevTrack sessions, 24x7 (7-minute lightning talks with each comprising no more than 24 slides) as well as a repository showdown and a poster session. The conference, hosted by the Chamlers University of Technology, was very well organized. The conference venue was the Clarion Hotel Post in central Göteborg. In total, 425 people from 45 countries attended the conference.</p> <p>The OR2024 full program is available in <a href="https://www.conftool.net/or2024/sessions.php">ConfTool</a>. Slides from the contributors can be found in the <a href="https://zenodo.org/communities/openrepos/records?q=&amp;f=subject%3AOR2024">Open Repositories Community in Zenodo</a>. In the following, we highlight some of the sessions we attended. Due to limited space, this report can only be considered selective and subjective.</p> <p>In the <a href="https://www.conftool.net/or2024/index.php?page=browseSessions&amp;form_session=439&amp;presentations=show">Repositories Implementations</a> session, researchers from Stanford University, Harvard University, and a team in the Netherlands (Leiden University, DANS, CNR-ISTI/OpenAIRE, and Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam) shared their experience in the planning and migration of existing digital repositories to modern data infrastructures in order to meet new requirements and/or to accommodate unexpected changes. All three presentations offered valuable advice. In the <a href="https://www.conftool.net/or2024/index.php?page=browseSessions&amp;form_session=448&amp;presentations=show">Repository Rodeo</a> panel, representatives from several repository software and services (including Dataverse, DSpace, EPrints, Fedora, InvenioRDM, Islandora, and Samvera) all engaged with the audience with the directions of their respective technical and community developments.</p> <p>Cheng-Jen Lee, the tech lead of the <em><a href="https://data.depositar.io/about">depositar</a></em>, the data repository we have been developing in Academia Sinica, gave a presentation on <em><a href="https://pid.depositar.io/ark:37281/k5h2q5h19">Bringing Computation and Reproducibility to a Data Repository Using Binder</a></em> at the <a href="https://www.conftool.net/or2024/index.php?page=browseSessions&amp;form_session=519&amp;presentations=show">Developer Track Session 2</a>. In the presentation, he detailed how to extend <a href="https://binderhub.readthedocs.io/">BinderHub</a> (a Kubernetes-based package powering the Binder service) to CKAN (software for managing and publishing datasets, and from which the <em>depositar</em> is derived) so users can easily create and share executable computing environments from datasets in the repository. In the <a href="https://www.conftool.net/or2024/index.php?page=browseSessions&amp;form_session=529&amp;presentations=show">Data Repositories and Lessons Learned</a> session, <em>depositar</em> project lead Tyng-Ruey Chuang gave a presentation on <em><a href="https://pid.depositar.io/ark:37281/k5n4c2v0n">Building An Open Repository for FAIR Data: Experience Sharing on Technologies, Communities, and Policies</a></em>. He talked about the <em>depositar</em> team’s experience in community outreach and policy dialogue, in addition to the technical development of the open source data repository itself. The other presentations in the session were from Princeton University, KTH Royal Institute of Technology, and a consortium of research libraries in Canada. We feel the presenters all stress the importance of careful planning and long-term commitment of research institutions for the repositories they operate.</p> <p>In the <a href="https://www.conftool.net/or2024/index.php?page=browseSessions&amp;form_session=523&amp;presentations=show">24x7: Technical Solutions</a> session, we would like to highlight two enjoyable presentations from the Czech Republic. Hana Vyčítalová, Petra Černohlávková, and David Gerner from the National Library of Technology shared their experience in moving from Invenio 1 to DSpace 7. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.12548342">Their presentation is stunning</a>. Martin Lhotak, Filip Kersch, and Petr Zabicka (Library of the Czech Academy of Sciences and Moravian Library in Brno) presented <a href="https://old.starfos.tacr.cz/en/project/DH23P03OVV033">Orbis Pictus</a>: a project to open up the graphic content of digital libraries to the public, in particular about developing a tool to identify persons by their images in digitized books. The <a href="https://www.conftool.net/or2024/index.php?page=browseSessions&amp;form_session=522&amp;presentations=show">Trends and the Future of Open</a> session is an overview of the research data landscape in Europe (but the observations are applicable elsewhere in the world). We recommend the readers to look into <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.12579359">the presentation from Richard David Jones</a> (Cottage Labs) where he reflected on his involvement in Open Access for the last 25 years. He provided insightful perspective on the current and future roles of repositories in improving global publishing equity.</p> <p>We wish to note we finally met John Kunze after corresponding with him for several years. He and Donny Winston organized a workshop on <a href="https://www.conftool.net/or2024/index.php?page=browseSessions&amp;form_session=496&amp;presentations=show">Getting Running with ARK Persistent Identifiers</a>. Using Archival Resource Key (ARK), the <em>depositar</em> team has developed <a href="https://github.com/depositar/ckanext-ark">a CKAN extension</a> for <a href="https://docs.depositar.io/en/stable/user-guide/ark-identifier.html">assigning persistent identifiers (PIDs) to datasets</a>. It is joyful to be able to meet, in person, the people who have helped us so much.</p> <p><a href="https://or2025.openrepositories.org/">The 20th International Conference on Open Repositories (OR2025)</a> will take place on June 15–18, 2025, in Chicago, Illinois, USA. The theme for the OR2025 conference is <em>Twenty Years of Progress, a Future of Possibilities</em>. The <a href="https://or2025.openrepositories.org/program/call-for-proposals/">Call for Proposals</a> is now open with a submission deadline of December 18, 2024.</p> <p>Our travels to attend the conference have been supported by the Institute of Information Science, Academia Sinica, and by the National Science and Technology Council of Taiwan.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/news/repository-rodeo_or2024.JPG" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/news/repository-rodeo_or2024.JPG" class="img-thumbnail" width="100%" height="auto" alt="Q&amp;A at the Repository Rodeo session, OR2024. Photo: Tyng-Ruey Chuang" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> <b>Q&amp;A at the Repository Rodeo session, OR2024. Photo: Tyng-Ruey Chuang.</b> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The depositar team attended the 19th International Conference on Open Repositories (OR2024) in Göteborg, Sweden, on June 3–6, 2024. Cheng-Jen Lee wrote a detailed report in Traditional Chinese. Below is a report from Tyng-Ruey Chuang in English.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Report on the Computational Social Science Conference, 28-29 October 2024, Barcelona</title><link href="https://lab.depositar.io/news/241115_1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Report on the Computational Social Science Conference, 28-29 October 2024, Barcelona"/><published>2024-11-15T06:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-11-15T06:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://lab.depositar.io/news/241115_1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lab.depositar.io/news/241115_1/"><![CDATA[<blockquote> <p>Tyng-Ruey Chuang recently attended a CODATA Executive Committee meeting in Barcelona and, proceeding it, the Computational Social Science Conference hosted by the Barcelona Supercomputing Center.</p> </blockquote> <p>Organized by the <a href="https://www.bsc.es/">Barcelona Supercomputing Center (BSC)</a>, <a href="https://codata.org/about-codata/">CODATA</a> and <a href="https://lacaixafoundation.org/en/">Fundació La Caixa</a>, the <em><a href="https://codata.org/events/conferences/computational-social-science-conference-2024/">Computational Social Science Conference: Innovative Methods, Research Workflows and Data Stewardship</a></em> was held on 28-29 October, 2024, in Barcelona at the campus of <a href="https://www.upc.edu/en/the-upc/the-institution">Universitat Politècnica de Catalunya (UPC)</a>. The conference is consisted of five sessions on the intertwined topics of data sciences and social sciences, with a lively lightning talks session, and starting with a keynote by David Lazer on <em>Building a Trans-Atlantic Coalition for Studying the Giants of the Internet</em>. The conference, overall, has been an intense two-day meeting with <a href="https://codata.org/events/conferences/computational-social-science-conference-2024/speakers-and-abstracts/">speakers giving expert overviews of the challenging issues faced and addressed by front-line social science researchers</a>. By our estimates, the conference was attended by about 150 researchers and students, with around a quarter of them traveling from abroad for the meeting.</p> <p>In his keynote, David Lazer (Northeastern University) talks about the problems in relying on social media platforms (e.g. the site formally known as Twitter) for human behavior data when doing academic research. He advocates instead a shared research infrastructure with voluntarily contributed user data, as exemplified by the <a href="https://nationalinternetobservatory.org/">National Internet Observatory</a> project funded by the National Science Foundation in the US. In the following, we then highlight some of the other talks given in the conference. Note that this report is not meant to be comprehensive and, due to limited space, can only be considered selective and subjective. Slides from some of the presentations can be found at the conference website.</p> <p>In the first session, Chico Camargo (University of Exeter) surveys the areas in which complexity scientists can work in the social sciences (among them, “social data science” and “cultural evolution and cultural analytics”) and emphasizes the interdisciplinarity of works. Marga Torre (Universidad Carlos III de Madrid, UC3M) reflects on the successful establishment of a Master degree program in Computational Social Science at UC3M and its future challenges (among them, “interdisciplinarity for real” and “strengthen collaboration between social scientists and computer scientists”). David Garcia (University of Konstanz) talks about simulating opinion dynamics among LLM agents with some implications in decision-making.</p> <p>The second session is about data modeling for social science with contributions from Hannes Mueller (Barcelona School of Economics), Shaily Gandhi (University of Salzburg), and Sebastian Poledna (International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis). The topics ranged from ethics in economic forecast and policy making, enhancing disaster response with social media analytics, to economic modeling by large-scale simulations. The session is followed by lightning talks of which we are especially impressed by a presentation on the Living Arrangements Project, a world-scale multilevel analysis on household composition and change. The presentation is given by Paolo Marangio and Nienke Visscher (BSC).</p> <p>The second day of the conference starts with a session with two presentations on the state-of-art practices in research data repositories. Stefano Iacus (Harvard University) updates the audience on the recent advances in the Dataverse Project and on how to use differential privacy to improve access to sensitive data while maintaining confidentiality. Darren Bell (UK Data Service) detailed the real-world issues in mediating access to data objects stored in research data repositories (among them, costly human mediation, unstructured access policies, and the lack of upstream access metadata).</p> <p>The fourth session is on data description for AI and machine analysis. Gyorgy Gyomai (OECD) explores how <a href="https://sdmx.org/">SDMX (Statistical Data and Metadata eXchange)</a>, a standard to improve data connectivity and machine readability, can be an enabler for AI applications. Elena Simperl (King’s College London) give an engaging presentation on <a href="http://mlcommons.org/croissant/1.0">Croissant</a>, a community-driven metadata format for AI-ready datasets. Christine Kirkpatrick (San Diego Supercomputer Center) overviews the works being carried out in research networks such as <a href="https://www.farr-rcn.org/">FARR (FAIR in ML, AI Readiness, and Reproducibility)</a> and <a href="https://fairdo.org/">FAIR Digital Objects (FDOs)</a>.</p> <p>Data provenance and research reproducibility is the subject of the last session of the conference. Tony Ross-Hellauer (Know Center Research) presents the <a href="https://tier2-project.eu/">TIER2 Project</a>, funded by the European Union’s Horizon research programme, and discusses reproducibility challenges in computational social science. Carole Goble (University of Manchester) introduces the <a href="https://www.researchobject.org/ro-crate/">RO-Crate (Research Object Crate)</a> FAIR Digital Object framework for reproducible computational processing. Rosa Badia (BSC) provides an overview of <a href="https://pypi.org/project/pycompss/">PyCOMPSs</a>, a programming environment for the development of workflow applications, as well as on how it can be used to support computational reproducibility in high-performance computing. This session is probably the most technical one of the entire conference. It is nevertheless very enjoyable for people, like us, with a background in Computer Science.</p> <p>The conference organizers also arranged a visit to <a href="https://www.bsc.es/marenostrum/marenostrum-5">MareNostrum 5</a>, an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/European_High-Performance_Computing_Joint_Undertaking">EuroHPC Joint Undertaking</a> supercomputer hosted at BSC. The MareNostrum 5 ACC (Accelerated Partition) has 1120 nodes with each equipped with two Intel 40-core CPUs and four Nvidia Hopper GPUs. The cluster has a peak performance of 260 PFlops</p> <p>We thank <a href="https://www.bsc.es/news/bsc-news/merc%C3%A8-crosas-elected-new-president-the-committee-data-the-international-science-council">Dr. Mercè Crosas</a> (CODATA President and the head of Computational Social Sciences at BSC) for the invitation to participate in this exciting conference. Our travel to attend the meetings has been supported by CODATA and the Institute of Information Science, Academia Sinica, Taiwan.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/news/Computational_Social_Science_UPC_20241029.JPG" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/news/Computational_Social_Science_UPC_20241029.JPG" class="img-fluid rounded" width="100%" height="auto" alt="Universitat Politècnica de Catalunya (UPC). Photo: Tyng-Ruey Chuang." loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> <b>Universitat Politècnica de Catalunya (UPC). Photo: Tyng-Ruey Chuang.</b> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Tyng-Ruey Chuang recently attended a CODATA Executive Committee meeting in Barcelona and, proceeding it, the Computational Social Science Conference hosted by the Barcelona Supercomputing Center.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">National Taiwan Normal University Open Access Week Lecture - From data repository to research data management practice</title><link href="https://lab.depositar.io/news/241029_1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="National Taiwan Normal University Open Access Week Lecture - From data repository to research data management practice"/><published>2024-10-29T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-10-29T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://lab.depositar.io/news/241029_1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lab.depositar.io/news/241029_1/"><![CDATA[<p>Please see the <a href="/zh-tw/news/241029_1/">announcement in Chinese</a> for details.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Please see the announcement in Chinese for details.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">depositar Syetem Update: Source Code Updated to Version v6.7.0</title><link href="https://lab.depositar.io/news/240830_1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="depositar Syetem Update: Source Code Updated to Version v6.7.0"/><published>2024-08-30T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-08-30T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://lab.depositar.io/news/240830_1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lab.depositar.io/news/240830_1/"><![CDATA[<p>The depositar system <a href="https://docs.depositar.io/en/stable/changelog.html#v6-7-0-2024-07-18">had been updated</a>! Please refer to <a href="https://lab.depositar.io/zh-tw/news/240830_1/">this post (in Mandarin)</a> for details.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The depositar system had been updated! Please refer to this post (in Mandarin) for details.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome, 2024 Summer Interns!</title><link href="https://lab.depositar.io/news/240702_1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome, 2024 Summer Interns!"/><published>2024-07-02T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-07-02T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://lab.depositar.io/news/240702_1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lab.depositar.io/news/240702_1/"><![CDATA[<p>We welcome five intern students to the depositar lab this summer! As part of the internship training, we organize short courses on <a href="https://rdm.depositar.io/">Research Data Management (RDM)</a>, structured text, git, and Jupyter Book (<a href="https://lab.depositar.io/zh-tw/news/240304_1/">see last year’s intern projects</a>), <a href="https://qgis.org/">QGIS</a>, <a href="https://www.openstreetmap.org/">OpenStreetMap</a>, <a href="https://www.wikidata.org">Wikidata</a>, and 360° photo/video documentation and processing:</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th>Course</th> <th>Instructor</th> <th>Date &amp; Time</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>RDM &amp; <em>depositar</em></td> <td>Chia-Hsun Ally Wang &amp; Ming-Syuan Ho</td> <td>July 2, 10:00 am</td> </tr> <tr> <td>git &amp; Jupyter Book</td> <td>Cheng-Jen Lee</td> <td>July 9, 10:00 am</td> </tr> <tr> <td>QGIS</td> <td>Hsiung-Ming Liao</td> <td>July 16, 10:00 am</td> </tr> <tr> <td>OpenStreetMap</td> <td>Dennis Raylin Chen</td> <td>July 17, 10:00 am</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Wikidata</td> <td>Dennis Raylin Chen</td> <td>July 24, 10:00 am</td> </tr> <tr> <td>360° photos/videos</td> <td>Yu-Huang Wang</td> <td>July 25, 10:00 am</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p><br/></p> <p>By giving these short courses, we hope to introduce the students to the basics of research data management and static website generation, as well as to the use and enrichment of communal resources of open geographic information and structured data. The courses will be held at the Institute of Information Science, Academia Sinica, and conducted in Taiwanese Mandarin. After taking these courses, the interns will work on personal projects.</p> <p>We are especially grateful to our guest lecturers: Hsiung-Ming Liao (GIS Center, RCHSS, Academia Sinica), Yu-Huang Wang (Nature Watch Ecological and Environmental Consultancy), and Dennis Raylin Chen (Wikimedia Taiwan).</p> <p>This year the summer internship students are from the National Cheng Kung University, the National Chung Cheng University, and the National Dong Hwa University in Taiwan, and from Vassar College in New York, USA.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We welcome five intern students to the depositar lab this summer! As part of the internship training, we organize short courses on Research Data Management (RDM), structured text, git, and Jupyter Book (see last year’s intern projects), QGIS, OpenStreetMap, Wikidata, and 360° photo/video documentation and processing:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">We are hiring!</title><link href="https://lab.depositar.io/news/240620_1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="We are hiring!"/><published>2024-06-20T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-06-20T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://lab.depositar.io/news/240620_1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lab.depositar.io/news/240620_1/"><![CDATA[<p>Please see the <a href="/zh-tw/news/240620_1/">announcement in Chinese</a> for details.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Please see the announcement in Chinese for details.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Retrospect and Prospect of Archiving for Contemporary Events: Case Studies from the 318 Civil Movment and Covid-19 Pandemic.</title><link href="https://lab.depositar.io/news/240528_1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Retrospect and Prospect of Archiving for Contemporary Events: Case Studies from the 318 Civil Movment and Covid-19 Pandemic."/><published>2024-05-28T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-05-28T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://lab.depositar.io/news/240528_1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lab.depositar.io/news/240528_1/"><![CDATA[<center> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/news/240528-1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/news/240528-1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/news/240528-1-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/news/240528-1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded" width="100%" height="auto" alt="黃恐龍 CC BY-ND 4.0 https://public.318.io/33719" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> </center> <div class="caption"> <b>(黃恐龍 CC BY-ND 4.0 https://public.318.io/33719)</b> </div> <blockquote> <p>本文由王家薰撰寫，並同步刊登於 <a href="https://www.scimonth.com.tw/archives/9916">2024-05-15 科技報導</a></p> </blockquote> <p>許多事件都會影響人們生活的軌跡，並成為群眾的共同記憶，包括社會運動與抗爭，例如野百合學運、太陽花公民運動（以下稱為318公民運動）；或全球盛行的傳染疾病，例如嚴重特殊傳染性肺炎（COVID-19）。隨著時間的推進，雖然許多影像或文字紀錄能夠被留存下來，但這些當代事件的痕跡卻會不斷地流失。</p> <p>研究資料寄存所實驗室過去有幸參與幾項重大事件的數位保存與資料協作專案，包含「<a href="https://public.318.io">318公民運動文物紀錄典藏庫計畫</a>」（簡稱318典藏庫）及「<a href="https://th.covid19.commons.tw/">COVID-19影像與敘述</a>」（簡稱COVID-19典藏庫）。</p> <p>318典藏庫及COVID-19典藏庫兩者因發生的場域及規模不同，採取的文物取得方式也相當迥異。318公民運動當時由中央研究院成立專案小組，至立法院主動採集文物，並陸續與現場直播的成員取得原生數位檔〔註1〕；而COVID-19相關的影像與敘述則開放由民眾自主上傳自己的防疫心情故事，並由國立臺灣歷史博物館邀請政府與民間各界撰寫分享，記錄這場全民防疫行動〔註2〕。以下簡述兩者的建立過程及現況。 <br/> <br/></p> <h3 id="318典藏庫讓大眾親近使用藏品">318典藏庫－讓大眾親近使用藏品</h3> <p>318典藏庫當初建置的目標，是希望所有藏品內容都可被大眾親近使用。為了達成目標，研究資料寄存所建立搜尋目錄系統，提供完善的後設資料欄位，盡可能完善填寫藏品內文及屬性（例如形式、內容描述），並在實體文物數位化後，鼓勵創作者指認自己的著作，選擇公眾授權（public licenses）釋出高解析度圖檔。此外也將含有個人資料的藏品做去識別化處置（例如明信片上的姓名及地址）等，詳細的系統建置細節及原則，讀者可以從〈當代事件之記憶：318公民運動文物紀錄典藏庫之建立〉（延伸閱讀1）這篇文章了解更多內容。</p> <p>開放資料有助於群眾回顧及研究使用。318典藏庫系統自2015年上線，至今共典藏2萬3435筆數位紀錄，其中採用公眾授權的藏品超過六成（共1萬4521筆）。這幾年來陸續有研究單位使用318典藏庫的藏品進行研究、發表論文，例如<a href="https://www.ir.nihon-u.ac.jp/pdf/research/publication/01_41_05.pdf">〈女性參與者在社會運動空間中的角色──以臺灣太陽花運動為例〉（社会運動空間における女性参加者のあり方──台湾ひまわり運動を事例に）</a>、<a href="https://ieas.directfrompublisher.com/catalog/book/sunflowers-and-umbrellas">〈太陽花和雨傘社會運動，表現力實踐和政治文化在臺灣和香港〉（Sunflowers and Umbrellas Social Movements, Expressive Practices, and Political Culture in Taiwan and Hong Kong）</a>，以及<a href="https://yorkspace.library.yorku.ca/items/a5f7ca03-cdc5-4306-bcaf-0dbd71c8ac7f">〈臺灣國族主義的視覺政治：太陽花運動意像中爭議的國族認同〉（The Visual Politics of Taiwanese Nationalism: Contested National Identities in the Imagery of the Sunflower Movement）</a>。而在過去幾個月的回顧活動裡，一些電影和電視製片人也將典藏庫的素材用於318公民運動十週年的<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TxaO1XYrRDQ">新聞報導</a>和<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ijo4Np3VJYM">紀錄片</a>。</p> <p>隨著時間的演進，像這類主題式的小型典藏記憶庫，如何持續維運並呈現藏品原始的面貌，也面臨到一些挑戰。例如因應系統老化，究竟需要升級系統，或是否將整個內容遷移到新的典藏管理系統（例如Omeka S）？此外，大部分的實體文物及數位化後的內容，雖已轉移至典藏機構（例如國立臺灣歷史博物館、國家文化記憶庫）永久典藏，但藏品內容樣貌複雜多元，典藏機構也有失去情境脈落及資源排擠的困難。例如一張臺灣島形狀的大型海報，本身由數百個令人鼓舞的便條紙所組成，便條紙與海報的部分與整體關係也保留在318典藏庫，但轉移至國家文化記憶庫後，則失去這個結構〔註3〕。讀者們可從<a href="https://archive-it.org/post/planning-for-long-term-access-to-covid-19-memory-websites/">〈抗爭的紀念物：反思太陽花運動典藏庫〉（Memorabilia of Protests: Reflecting on the Sunflower Movement Archive，延伸閱讀2）</a>文獲得一些作者的觀察。</p> <center> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/news/240528-3-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/news/240528-3-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/news/240528-3-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/news/240528-3.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded" width="100%" height="auto" alt="318公民運動文物紀錄典藏庫藏品。（318公民運動文物紀錄典藏庫計畫）" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> </center> <div class="caption"> <b>318公民運動文物紀錄典藏庫藏品。（318公民運動文物紀錄典藏庫計畫）</b> </div> <p><br/> <br/></p> <h3 id="covid-19典藏庫自行上傳疫情下的日常">COVID-19典藏庫－自行上傳疫情下的日常</h3> <p>相較於318典藏庫的經驗，為了保存COVID-19時期非固定場域多元面貌的臺灣社會景象，中央研究院資訊科學研究所、國立臺灣歷史博物館、拾穗者文化共同合作，於2020年6月即建置COVID-19典藏庫，提供大眾自由註冊、上傳照片並撰寫心情故事，以記錄臺灣在疫情下的日常風景。</p> <p>與318典藏庫由專案小組蒐集資料不同，COVID-19典藏庫採由民眾自主上傳紀錄的方式，自2020年6月開始徵集，至去（2023）年4月臺灣疫情趨於穩定後停止收件，近三年的時間共徵集到464則心情故事。所徵集到的影像記錄經博物館人員選取後，部分再轉至國家文化記憶庫典藏。例如麻豆國小疫情聯絡簿，反映學生疫情下的學校生活及沒有畢業典禮的無奈。</p> <p>由於COVID-19典藏庫建置於疫情初期，實屬「零預算」、「快速」收集及呈現資料的系統，且預計任務完成後就只保留資料，系統不一定會永久留存，以免除維護上的成本。因此系統從設計之初，便採用讓資料可自系統抽離、並搭配第三方服務的方式來進行長期的資料保存，例如將抽離後獲得的資料整理為資料集（dataset），存放於公開的儲存庫，民眾也可以自由下載打包藏品壓縮檔做保存。原始系統的網頁介面，也可透過第三方服務，例如<a href="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</a>的<a href="https://wayback-api.archive.org/">Wayback Machine</a>典藏原始網頁的樣貌。</p> <center> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/news/240528-2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/news/240528-2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/news/240528-2-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/news/240528-2.png" class="img-fluid rounded" width="100%" height="auto" alt="（CC BY 4.0 疫情聯絡簿）" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> </center> <div class="caption"> <b><a href="https://th.covid19.commons.tw/occurrence/2001403">CC BY 4.0 疫情聯絡簿</a></b> </div> <p><br/> <br/></p> <h3 id="面向未來的數位典藏工作">面向未來的數位典藏工作</h3> <p>318公民運動在今年適逢十週年，無論是實體或線上，都充滿了各種回顧活動，這類資料庫也扮演了重要的角色。不過，或許在各種回顧中，也可以從「典藏事件」的視角出發作探討，倘若「文物保存」是諸多後續研究的基礎，那麼這些與當代事件有關的數位典藏計畫，在未來又可以讓我們學到什麼？</p> <p>當代典藏工作是一份面向未來的工作，未來的人們手邊要有什麼樣的工具及素材，方能研究我們這個時代的歷史？這是需要持續思考嘗試解決的問題。希望透過我們的經驗分享，可以吸引大家更多的關注，並激發關於當代事件典藏的更多討論。</p> <center> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/news/240528-4-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/news/240528-4-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/news/240528-4-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/news/240528-4.png" class="img-fluid rounded" width="100%" height="auto" alt="COVID-19典藏庫" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> </center> <div class="caption"> <b>COVID-19典藏庫</b> </div> <p><br/> <br/> (感謝我們一直以來的合作夥伴，包含國立臺灣歷史博物館、拾穗者文化、絆談客股份有限公司，過去協助相關的典藏系統的建置及內容的收藏，最後感謝中央研究院資訊科學研究所莊庭瑞副研究員、李承鑫、中央研究院資訊科技創新研究中心何明諠、James X. Morris，協助編輯校讀，提升本文在內容上的精確性。)</p> <p>〔註1〕〈中研院搶救太陽花學運文物開放作者線上指認〉（自由時報）。<a href="https://news.ltn.com.tw/news/life/breakingnews/1486555">https://news.ltn.com.tw/news/life/breakingnews/1486555</a></p> <p>〔註2〕〈民眾可上傳防疫照片及故事臺史博再推出防疫資料蒐集2.0〉（臺灣台灣歷史博物館）。<a href="https://www.nmth.gov.tw/News_Content.aspx?n=4233&amp;s=134834">https://www.nmth.gov.tw/News_Content.aspx?n=4233&amp;s=134834</a></p> <p>〔註3〕存放在國家文化紀念庫中的318公民運動海報。<a href="https://memory.culture.tw/Home/Detail?Id=11000117386&amp;IndexCode=MOCCOLLECTIONS">https://memory.culture.tw/Home/Detail?Id=11000117386&amp;IndexCode=MOCCOLLECTIONS</a></p> <p><br/> <br/></p> <h3 id="延伸閱讀">延伸閱讀</h3> <ol> <li>莊庭瑞、曾沅芷。（2017）。<a href="https://www.archives.gov.tw/Book/MPBookList.aspx?cnid=1680&amp;p=1203">當代事件之記憶：318公民運動文物紀錄典藏庫之建立。檔案半年刊，16（2）</a>。</li> <li>Tyng-Ruey Chuang. (2023). <a href="https://archive-it.org/post/planning-for-long-term-access-to-covid-19-memory-websites/">Planning for Long-Term Access to COVID-19 Memory Websites.</a></li> <li>Tyng-Ruey Chuang. (2024). <a href="https://archive-it.org/post/reflecting-on-the-sunflower-movement/">Memorabilia of Protests: Reflecting on the Sunflower Movement Archive.</a></li> </ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[(黃恐龍 CC BY-ND 4.0 https://public.318.io/33719) 本文由王家薰撰寫，並同步刊登於 2024-05-15 科技報導]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">depositar Update: Binder User Manual is Available</title><link href="https://lab.depositar.io/news/240524_1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="depositar Update: Binder User Manual is Available"/><published>2024-05-24T02:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-05-24T02:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://lab.depositar.io/news/240524_1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lab.depositar.io/news/240524_1/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="更新內容">更新內容</h3> <p>研究資料寄存所 (depositar) 在去年十月底整合 <a href="https://binder.depositar.io/">Binder</a> 之後，使用者已可直接透過 depositar 建立運算環境，重現或展示用程式完成的研究結果，且過程中不須安裝任何軟體或套件。研究資料寄存所與 Binder 的整合，將有助於研究結果的運算可再現性，請參考<a href="https://rdm.depositar.io/zh_TW/news/20240315-computational-reproducibility-with-binder/">研究資料管理推進室 (RDM Hub)</a> 上的介紹（該短文亦刊於<a href="https://www.scimonth.com.tw/archives/8841">《科技報導》</a>）。</p> <p>為了讓所有人都能順利使用 Binder，在本月中，我們於使用手冊新增了 <a href="https://docs.depositar.io/zh-tw/6.6.6/user-guide/binder.html#">Binder 的章節</a>。</p> <p>如今只要點擊 depositar 右上選單的「<a href="https://data.depositar.io/zh_Hant_TW/help">支援</a>」，即可在操作手冊中，找到 Binder 服務的使用說明。</p> <p>如同 depositar 的其他功能，Binder 的使用說明也提供了中、英雙語言的版本，使用者可透過切換網站介面的語言分別進行檢視。</p> <div class="row" style="margin-bottom:35px;"> <div class="col-8"> <img src="/assets/img/news/2024-05-24_Binder-menu.jpg" alt="binder-zh" height="300px"/> <img src="/assets/img/news/2024-05-24_Binder-menu-en.jpg" alt="binder-en" height="300px"/></div> </div> <h3 id="補充資訊">補充資訊</h3> <ol> <li>使用者可提供「環境設定檔」，讓 Binder 建立程式運作的初始環境。詳細操作可見操作手冊 <a href="https://docs.depositar.io/zh-tw/6.6.6/user-guide/binder.html#id6">支援運算環境與客製化</a> 一節。</li> <li>Binder 仍是 depositar 的測試版功能，如有問題，可隨時 <a href="mailto:data.contact@depositar.io">聯繫我們</a>。</li> </ol> <h3 id="更新版本號">更新版本號</h3> <p><a href="https://docs.depositar.io/en/stable/changelog.html#v6-6-6-2024-05-15">v. 6.6.6</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[更新內容 研究資料寄存所 (depositar) 在去年十月底整合 Binder 之後，使用者已可直接透過 depositar 建立運算環境，重現或展示用程式完成的研究結果，且過程中不須安裝任何軟體或套件。研究資料寄存所與 Binder 的整合，將有助於研究結果的運算可再現性，請參考研究資料管理推進室 (RDM Hub) 上的介紹（該短文亦刊於《科技報導》）。]]></summary></entry></feed>